<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Blogs | Garrett Nay]]></title>
  <link href="http://garrettn.github.io/blog/categories/blogs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://garrettn.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-02T07:48:14-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://garrettn.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Garrett Nay]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We're All Learning Here]]></title>
    <link href="http://garrettn.github.io/blog/2013/10/01/were-all-learning-here/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-01T18:43:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://garrettn.github.io/blog/2013/10/01/were-all-learning-here</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello, world! Here&rsquo;s another blog about web development. I&rsquo;m a relative newcomer
to the web development industry, and while it may seem pointless to add yet
another entry to the roster of dev blogs out there, I have several reasons for
wanting to do it:</p>

<!--more-->


<ul>
<li><p>I&rsquo;ve been using open-source software heavily for several years now, and I&rsquo;m
starting to feel the urge to jump in and become a more active part of the
community.</p></li>
<li><p>I learn things better when I teach them to others, so as I&rsquo;m learning (and I
have a lot to learn!) I want to use this blog as a vehicle to explain what I&rsquo;m
learning, and thus hopefully solidify my own understanding.</p></li>
<li><p>It works as an &ldquo;accountability journal,&rdquo; encouraging me to more actively work
on my projects so I have something to write about.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> is really fun to use.</p></li>
<li><p>Above all, I hope that, once in a while, <strong>I&rsquo;ll be able to help somebody</strong>.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>That last reason is the most important. As I said before, I&rsquo;m fairly new to web
development, and for the past year-and-a-half or so I have been devouring
information on it wherever I can get it. Sites like the <a href="http://hub.tutsplus.com">Tuts+ network</a> are
incredible sources of knowledge that I&rsquo;ve benefited from extensively. But also,
there are lots of those lesser-known personal dev blogs that I&rsquo;ve received a lot
of help from. These are developers that write about the work they do, and when
they come across tricky problems or discover cool new ways of doing things, they
write about that so that everyone else can benefit from their experience. Many
times I have turned to the Internet with some baffling problem and found the
answer on some blog I&rsquo;d never heard of.</p>

<p>That is what I want this blog to be. I hope that in documenting my experiences
as a developer, I can help some other learner who is dealing with the same
problems I have found. After all, we&rsquo;re all learning here in this industry, and
we all have something to teach each other.</p>

<p>So thank you for reading, and here&rsquo;s to learning!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
