<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Meta | Garrett Nay]]></title>
  <link href="http://garrettn.github.io/blog/categories/meta/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://garrettn.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-02T07:48:14-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://garrettn.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Garrett Nay]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Obligatory Redesign Post]]></title>
    <link href="http://garrettn.github.io/blog/2014/06/10/the-obligatory-redesign-post/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-10T07:00:48-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://garrettn.github.io/blog/2014/06/10/the-obligatory-redesign-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hi. Yes, I&rsquo;m still here. And check out my new design! It may not look like much, but it represents a big step for me.</p>

<p>You see, ever since I started this Octopress blog, I always had this nagging feeling that I should do something about the design. The default Octopress theme is nice, but nobody wants to stick with the default theme, right? It&rsquo;s like how Twitter Bootstrap looks nice, but it&rsquo;s so nice that for a while it seemed as if half of the Web were using it. You could spot a Bootstrap-based site immediately (still can, I suppose). And you could pin my blog as an Octopress blog immediately, too. Not that that was a bad thing, but I didn&rsquo;t want this to get written off as &ldquo;yet another Octopress blog.&rdquo;</p>

<p>I wanted to create a new theme. Oh, I had big plans. I envisioned adapting one of the awesome templates by <a href="http://html5up.net">HTML5 Up</a>, and eventually open-sourcing it so everyone could easily integrate it into their own Octopress blogs. But then some things started happening in <a href="https://twitter.com/octopress">the Octopress world</a> that put me in stop-and-wait mode for quite a while.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Octopress 3?</h2>

<p>A few months ago, I learned that <a href="https://twitter.com/imathis">Brandon Mathis</a>, the creator of Octopress, is working on version 3.0 of the project. This isn&rsquo;t just an evolution of version 2&mdash;it&rsquo;s a completely new way of working. It&rsquo;s so different, in fact, that he created <a href="https://github.com/octopress/octopress">a new repository</a> for it. Octopress 3.0 is a Ruby gem rather than just a Git repository that you clone and modify, which is how 2.0 works. And all its various components are separated out into individual gems, including the way <a href="https://github.com/octopress/ink">themes and plugins</a> work.</p>

<p>And when I heard about this new version, it sounded like it was going to have a stable release very soon, so I thought, cool, I would wait and see how the whole thing worked, and then I could migrate my blog and apply my new theme using the new system.</p>

<p>Fast forward a few months, and Octopress 3.0 still isn&rsquo;t <em>quite</em> done. To be more precise, the Octopress gem is pretty much there, but Octopress Ink, the plugin and theme framework, is still being worked on. I believe it&rsquo;s almost ready, but the documentation is still very sparse, and I don&rsquo;t think I have the time or the energy to dig into it and figure out how it works for myself, especially since I know very little Ruby.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t get me wrong. I don&rsquo;t blame Brandon at all for having this take longer than planned. That&rsquo;s just how things go sometimes, and he clearly wants this to be the best product it can be. But because of the long delay, I started thinking about turning to other solutions.</p>

<h2>What About This Assemble Thing?</h2>

<p>Perhaps you&rsquo;ve heard of <a href="http://assemble.io">Assemble</a>, the static site generator for Node.js. It&rsquo;s essentially the Node counterpart of Ruby&rsquo;s Jekyll, which Octopress is based on. It works as a Grunt plugin, and it even has a Yeoman generator, the bottom line being that it uses technologies that I&rsquo;m much more familiar with.</p>

<p>I was excited about Assemble for a while. Since it uses Grunt, a tool I now have a fair amount of experience with, I could potentially customize my blog to be exactly how I wanted it, including the theme. The possibilities seemed endless.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, the Assemble project is still fairly young, and its documentation is pretty limited. I searched long and hard for information on how I could make Assemble work as a replacement for Octopress, but all I could find was partial answers. There is also some functionality that I need that isn&rsquo;t quite there yet.</p>

<p>I know, Assemble is an open-source project&mdash;including its documentation&mdash;and instead of complaining about it I should just contribute to making it better. And I really might someday. But when it comes down to it, I have to decide: How much time and energy am I willing to invest in hacking on my blog, when simpler solutions are available?</p>

<h2>Sticking with Version 2 For Now</h2>

<p>Sometimes, even with all the desire for hacking and customizing, you just want it to work. And the fact of the matter is that Octopress 2 does work for me. There are a few hiccups now and then, mainly dealing with syntax highlighting, which I hope will be improved in the new version. But overall it has been a solid blogging platform, one that is simple to set up and simple to work with.</p>

<p>So in the end, I&rsquo;ve decided to stay with Octopress version 2 for the time being. I&rsquo;ll keep watching the progress on version 3, because I&rsquo;m still eager to upgrade when the time is right. I&rsquo;ll also keep tabs on Assemble because I still want to take advantage of it some day, if not for this blog, then for other projects. But as for me and my dev blog, we will use Octopress 2.</p>

<p>Having decided that, I looked around for a theme that would work with Octopress 2. It didn&rsquo;t need to be anything fancy, just something different enough from the default. Turns out there are <a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress/wiki/3rd-Party-Octopress-Themes">quite a few themes</a> available, and some have even been created quite recently. And now that I&rsquo;ve found a theme that I&rsquo;m happy with (after a few tweaks), I feel like I can keep writing on this blog without that redesign monkey on my back.</p>

<h2>For the Record&mdash;Theme Details</h2>

<p>I feel I should give credit where credit is due. The design of this blog is mostly thanks to the work of people more skilled than I.</p>

<ul>
<li>The theme is 95% based on <a href="https://github.com/johnkeith/boldandblue">Bold and Blue</a> by <a href="http://www.johnkeith.us">John Keith</a>.</li>
<li>The sans-serif font (modified from the original theme) is <a href="http://mozilla.github.io/Fira">Fira Sans</a>, an open-source font provided by Mozilla.</li>
<li>The speckled noise background in the header comes from the <a href="http://philbit.com/svgpatterns/">SVG Patterns Library</a>.</li>
<li>The social icons were provided by <a href="http://icomoon.io">IcoMoon</a>.</li>
</ul>


<p>Okay, now that the obligatory redesign post is out of the way, let&rsquo;s move on to brighter age of dev blogging!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We're All Learning Here]]></title>
    <link href="http://garrettn.github.io/blog/2013/10/01/were-all-learning-here/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-01T18:43:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://garrettn.github.io/blog/2013/10/01/were-all-learning-here</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello, world! Here&rsquo;s another blog about web development. I&rsquo;m a relative newcomer
to the web development industry, and while it may seem pointless to add yet
another entry to the roster of dev blogs out there, I have several reasons for
wanting to do it:</p>

<!--more-->


<ul>
<li><p>I&rsquo;ve been using open-source software heavily for several years now, and I&rsquo;m
starting to feel the urge to jump in and become a more active part of the
community.</p></li>
<li><p>I learn things better when I teach them to others, so as I&rsquo;m learning (and I
have a lot to learn!) I want to use this blog as a vehicle to explain what I&rsquo;m
learning, and thus hopefully solidify my own understanding.</p></li>
<li><p>It works as an &ldquo;accountability journal,&rdquo; encouraging me to more actively work
on my projects so I have something to write about.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> is really fun to use.</p></li>
<li><p>Above all, I hope that, once in a while, <strong>I&rsquo;ll be able to help somebody</strong>.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>That last reason is the most important. As I said before, I&rsquo;m fairly new to web
development, and for the past year-and-a-half or so I have been devouring
information on it wherever I can get it. Sites like the <a href="http://hub.tutsplus.com">Tuts+ network</a> are
incredible sources of knowledge that I&rsquo;ve benefited from extensively. But also,
there are lots of those lesser-known personal dev blogs that I&rsquo;ve received a lot
of help from. These are developers that write about the work they do, and when
they come across tricky problems or discover cool new ways of doing things, they
write about that so that everyone else can benefit from their experience. Many
times I have turned to the Internet with some baffling problem and found the
answer on some blog I&rsquo;d never heard of.</p>

<p>That is what I want this blog to be. I hope that in documenting my experiences
as a developer, I can help some other learner who is dealing with the same
problems I have found. After all, we&rsquo;re all learning here in this industry, and
we all have something to teach each other.</p>

<p>So thank you for reading, and here&rsquo;s to learning!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
